A Guide to the Directors correspondence and subject files of the Commission on Population Growth and Development, 1967-1995 (bulk 1989-1994)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Directors correspondence and subject files of the Commission on Population Growth and Development, 1967-1995 (bulk 1989-1994)
The Library of Virginia
35064, 35772, 36388, 50419
32 cu. ft. (32 boxes)
Virginia. General Assembly. Commission on Population Growth and Development.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Commission on Population Growth and Development, Richmond, Va., 30 March 1995 [Acc. 35064].
Transferred from the Division of Legislative Services, General Assembly Building, Richmond, Va. 23219, 2 April 1998 [Acc. 35772].
Transferred from the Commission on Population Growth and Development, Richmond, Va., 8 March 1999 [Acc. 36388].
Transferred from unknown, Retrospective accessioning, 25 May 2012 [Acc. 50419].
Biographical Information
The Commission on Population Growth and Development was established by House Joint Resolution No. 435 during the 1989 General Assembly Session to evaluate and recommend a statewide planning process for population growth and development in Virginia to the year 2020. The Commission was established in response to a recommendation by the Year 2020 Panel that each state participating in the Chesapeake Bay Agreement develop ways to implement the recommendations contained in the Panel's report according to its legislative, executive and budgetary commitments and priorities. This Year 2020 Panel was established as part of the Chesapeake Bay Agreement of 1987 to study the consequences of population growth and development on the Chesapeake Bay watershed.
The Commission on Population Growth and Development was established to study and evaluate the consequences of present and anticipated changes in population and patterns of development on the economic vitality and environmental health of all regions of the Commonwealth. The Commission was also charged with developing initiatives to ensure that adequate planning, coordination, and data dissemination occur at all levels of government, with recommending alternatives for meeting funding requirements, with proposing innovative and cooperative land management techniques, and with examining and evaluating methods of coordinating the activities of the General Assembly and state agencies as they relate to population growth and development.
The Commission was composed of thirty-three members representing the Virginia General Assembly, local and regional government, and citizens at large and was to report annually its findings and recommendations to the Governor and the General Assembly. The provisions of the chapter expired on June 30, 1995 when the Commission was not extended by the General Assembly. The chairman of the commission was Delegate Tayloe W. Murphy, Jr., and the executive director of the commission was Katherine Imhoff.
Scope and Content
Records, 1967-1995 (bulk 1989-1994), of the Commission on Population Growth and Development. Includes clippings, correspondence, faxes, House and Senate documents, meeting minutes, publications, public meetings and participant comments, reports, speeches, subject files, surveys, and other materials. The collection is arranged into four series by accession number and has been processed using minimal processing standards.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Directors correspondence and subject files [Acc. 35064]
Series II: Directors correspondence and subject files [Acc. 35772]
Series III: Directors correspondence and subject files [Acc. 36388]
Series IV: Directors correspondence and subject files [Acc. 50419]
Contents List
- Series I: Directors correspondence and subject files [Acc. 35064], 1989-1994, Extent: 4 cu. ft. (4 boxes). (Box 1-3)
  This series includes correspondence, faxes, historical documents, and participation meeting files.
  - Subseries 1: Public Education and Participation Meetings, 1991 October
    Open public education and participation meetings on "the Challenge of Growth" were coordinated by the Commission on Population Growth and Development to inform citizens of future trends and the work of the Commission, and to give citizens the opportunity to express their opinions on a variety of issues. This subseries documents these public meetings and include correspondence, planning documentation, informational papers, new releases, memorandums, schedules, and Virginia Visions Worksheets, which were comment forms completed by meeting participants.
    - General information (policies, findings, correspondence, planning documents, etc.), 1991 October (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General hand-outs for all meetings, 1991 October (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Richmond Regional and Crater PDCs, General information, 1991 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Richmond Regional and Crater PDCs, Participant comments and worksheets, 1991 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Northern Neck, Middle Peninsula, and RADCO PDCs, General Information, 1991 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Northern Neck, Middle Peninsula, and RADCO PDCs, Participant comments and worksheets, 1991 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Northern Virginia PDC, General information, 1991 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Northern Virginia PDC, Participant comments and worksheets, 1991 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Accomack-Northampton PDC, General information and participant comments and worksheets, 1991 October 8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Central Virginia, Southside, and Piedmont PDCs, General information and participant comments and worksheets, 1991 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Thomas Jefferson and Central Shenandoah PDC, General information, 1991 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Thomas Jefferson and Central Shenandoah PDC, Participant comments and worksheets, 1991 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lord Fairfax and Rappahannock-Rapidan PDCs, General information, 1991 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - LENOWISCO, Cumberland and Mt. Rogers PDCs, General information, 1991 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - New River, Fifth and West Piedmont PDCs, General information, 1991 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Hampton Roads PDC, General information, 1991 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Hampton Roads PDC, Participant comments and worksheets, 1991 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Summaries of public meetings, 1991 October (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Report of October 1991 Public meetings, 1991 October (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 2: Background Information and History Files, 1967-1994
    This subseries includes mailing lists, speeches, notes, discussion papers, policy statements, agendas, correspondence, minutes, and various publications.
    - Commission documents: HJR 435 materials, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Commission documents: Notes on circular balance, ca. 1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Commission documents: Previous Virginia legislative acts related to growth and development planning, 1968-1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Commission documents: Chesapeake Bay Commission agendas and minutes, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Commission documents: Meeting materials, 1989 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Commission documents: Meeting materials, 1989 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Commission documents: Meeting materials, 1989 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Commission documents: Meeting materials, 1989 October 25-26 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Commission documents: Meeting materials, 1989 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Commission documents: Commission Report drafts, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Commission documents: Virginia Growth Management Forum, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Commission documents: General notes, reports, and correspondence, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Commission documents: Maryland - Growth and development legislation, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Commission documents: Commission Report, 1990 January (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Commission documents: General notes, reports, and correspondence, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Commission documents: General notes, reports, and correspondence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Background information: Georgia - Growth and development strategies, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Background information: Clippings (newspapers), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Background information: Articles (journals), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Background information: Newsletters (mostly related to the Chesapeake Bay), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Publications: Cooperative Forecasting: Summary (Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Publications: Population Growth and Development in the Chesapeake Bay Watershed to the Year 2020 (Chesapeake Executive Council), 1988 December (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Publications: Chesapeake Bay Program - Chesapeake Bay Watershed Development Policies and Guidelines Agreement Commitment Report (Chesapeake Executive Council), 1989 January (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Publications: A State Role in Guiding Local Growth Management (Va. Dept. of Housing and Community Development), 1989 July (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Publications: State Land Conservation and Growth Management Policy: A Legislator's Guide (National Conference on State Legislatures), 1990 April (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Publications: Report of the Virginia Metropolitan Area Study Commission (Senate Doc. 16), 1967 (Box 1A, Folder 1)
    - Publications: Executive Management Responsibilities, Staff Documents, V. 1 (Commission on State Governmental Management), 1976 (Box 1A, Folder 2)
    - Publications: Report on the Comparative Revenue Capacity, Revenue Effort and Fiscal Stress of Virginia's Counties and Cities 1988/1989 (Commission on Local Government), 1991 September (Box 1A, Folder 3)
    - Publications: Virginia Geographic Information Network, Revised Technical Memorandum, 1993 April (Box 1A, Folder 4)
    - Publications: Virginia Geographic Information Network, Briefing, 1993 December (Box 1A, Folder 5)
    - Publications: Virginia Geographic Information Network, Project Documentation, 1993 October (Box 1A, Folder 6)
    - Publications: Virginia Geographic Information Network, Situation Assessment and Strategic Recommendation, 1993 August (Box 1A, Folder 7)
    - Publications: Virginia Geographic Information Network, Proposal for Legislative Action, 1993 August (Box 1A, Folder 8)
    - Publications: Reference Material prepared for Joint Subcommittee Studying Regional Service Delivery HJR 281 (Commission on Local Government), 1994 August (Box 1A, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 3: Incoming faxes, 1991-1994
    - 1991 April-September (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1991 October-December (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1992 January-April (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1992 May-June (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1992 July-August (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1992 September-October (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1992 November-December (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1993 January (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1993 February-March (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1993 April (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1993 May (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1993 June (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1993 July (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1993 August (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1993 September (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1993 October-December (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1994 January (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1994 February (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1994 March (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1994 April (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1994 May (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 1994 June (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 1994 July (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 1994 August (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 1994 September (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 1994 October (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 1994 November-December (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Subseries 4: Outgoing faxes, 1991-1994
    - 1991 March-April (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - 1991 May (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - 1991 June (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - 1991 July (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - 1991 August (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - 1991 September (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - 1991 October (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1991 November (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1991 December (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1992 January-February (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1992 March (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1992 April (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1992 May (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1992 June (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1992 July (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1992 August (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 1992 September (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 1992 October (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - 1992 November (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - 1992 December (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - 1993 January (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 1993 February (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - 1993 March (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 1993 April (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - 1993 May (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - 1993 June (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - 1993 July (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - 1993 August (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - 1993 September (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - 1993 October (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - 1993 November (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 1993 December (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - 1994 January (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - 1994 February (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 1994 March (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - 1994 April (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - 1994 May (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - 1994 June (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - 1994 July (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - 1994 August (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - 1994 September (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - 1994 October (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - 1994 November (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Series II: Directors correspondence and subject files [Acc. 35772], 1990-1994, Extent: 4 cu. ft. (4 boxes). (Box 1-4)
  - GIS/VGIN Information (Articles, Correspondence, and reports), 1994 (Box 1)
  - Data Committee Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Local government and GIS contacts, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Briefing, 1994 September (Box 1)
  - Summary of the DATA Project, 1994 (Box 1)
  - NSGIC, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Future Development of the Commonwealth, 1993 (Box 2)
  - VGIN, Briefing, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Population Growth and Development Comprehensive Data Project, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Metropolitan Sprawl in Virginia, 1994 (Box 2)
  - State Technology Advisory Committee, 1991-1993 (Box 2)
  - Commonwealth Population Growth and Development, Public meetings, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Regional Resource Issues, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Data Project Overheads, 1991-1994 (Box 3)
  - GIS Contacts, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Local Government Survey, 1992 (Box 3)
  - GIS Survey, Results, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Geographic and Biological Land-Use Information and Mapping Systems Study, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 3)
  - Working paper (585), 1992 (Box 3)
  - Shenandoah National Park Related Lands Study, 1993 (Box 3)
  - GIS, Other states, 1991-1994 (Box 3)
  - Local Government Handbook, 1994 (Box 4)
  - GIS, Situation Assessment, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Proposal for Legislative Action, 1993 (Box 4)
  - PDC Memo of Agreement, 1993 (Box 4)
  - RPA, GIS Project, 1993 (Box 4)
  - DATA Project, 1993 (Box 4)
  - GIS Project, Contract and correspondence, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 4)
- Series III: Directors correspondence and subject files [Acc. 36388], 1972-1995 (bulk 1989-1994), Extent: 11 cu. ft. (11 boxes). (Box 1-11)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1991 August 7-8 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1991 September 4 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1991 November 21-22 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1992 April 30-May 1 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1992 June 18-19 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1992 October 1-2 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1992 November 16 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1993 March 17 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1993 August 5 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1993 September 29 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1994 January 4 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1994 March 30 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1994 April 13 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1994 July 11 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1994 September 9 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1994 October 11-13 (Box 1)
  - Commission on Population Growth and Development, Meeting records, 1994 December 5 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee, Meeting records, 1992 January 20 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee, Meeting records, 1992 March 12 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee, Meeting records, 1992 August 20 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee, Meeting records, 1992 December 2 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee, Meeting records, 1993 January 14 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee, Meeting records, 1993 July 22 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee, Meeting records (Also Drafting Committee), 1993 September 28 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee, Meeting records, 1994 July 25-26 (Box 1)
  - Data Committee, Meeting records, 1993 May 17 (Box 2)
  - Drafting Committee, Meeting records, 1993 August 22-23 (Box 2)
  - Public Education and Participation Committee, Meeting records, 1991 October (Box 2)
  - Publications, Report to the Governor and General Assembly (H.D. No. 40), 1990 (Box 2)
  - Publications, Findings and a Plan for Action, 1991 March (Box 2)
  - Publications, Points of Discussion: Finance Committee, 1991 July (Box 2)
  - Publications, Points of Discussion: Governance Committee, 1991 July (Box 2)
  - Publications, Points of Discussion: Resources Committee, 1991 July (Box 2)
  - Publications, Policy Paper, 1991 September (Box 2)
  - Publications, Public meeting on "The Challenge of Growth," 1991 October (Box 2)
  - Publications, Report on October Public Meeting, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Publications, Virginians Respond: A Report of the October Public Meetings, 1991 December (Box 2)
  - Publications, Report to the Governor and General Assembly (H.D. No. 41), 1992 (Box 2)
  - Publications, A Changing Virginia, 1992 September (Box 2)
  - Publications, Mapping Applications in Virginia: Results of a Survey on GIS, 1992 November (Box 2)
  - Publications, Report to the Governor and General Assembly (H.D. No. 72), 1993 (Box 2)
  - Publications, GIS Technical Report, 1993 October (Box 2)
  - Publications, Report to the Governor and General Assembly (H.D. No. 76), 1994 (Box 2)
  - Publications, A Historical Overview of State and Regional Planning in Virginia, 1994 June (Box 2)
  - Publications, Growth Management and Strategic Planning: A Background Reader, 1994 July (Box 2)
  - Publications, GIS Handbook for Local Governments in Virginia, 1994 September (Box 2)
  - Publications, Metropolitan Sprawl in Virginia, 1994 December (Box 2)
  - Publications, History of Growth Commission, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Publications, Overhead materials, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft I, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft I (Committee comments), 1992 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft II, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft II (Presentation materials), 1992 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft III, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft III (Presentation materials), 1993 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft IV, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft IV (Presentation materials), 1993 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft IV (Proposed changes), 1993 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft IV to V (Proposed changes), 1993 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft V, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft V (Speaking points), 1993 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft V to VI (Changes), 1993 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft VI (Final Version), 1993 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Draft VI (Final Version, Presentation materials), 1993 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, Notes, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, HB 1068, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, SB 323, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, Virginia Growth Strategies Act, HB 1068, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, General, HB 787, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, General, HJR 640, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, General, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, General, Area Development Act, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, General, Budget Amendment Act, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, General, Virginia Geographic Information Network, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Legislative Files, Legislation, General, Virginia Strategic Planning Act, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Subject files, Additional goals, 1989-1995 (Box 4)
  - Subject files, Advisory Council, 1989-1995 (Box 4)
  - Subject files, Budget, General, 1989-1995 (Box 4)
  - Subject files, Budget, Budget reports, 1989-1995 (Box 4)
  - Subject files, Budget, Commission on Population Growth and Development, 1989-1995 (Box 4)
  - Subject files, Budget, Division of Planning, 1989-1995 (Box 4)
  - Subject files, Budget, Response to budget addenda, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Subject files, Budget, Tax bill money request, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Subject files, Background information on the Commission, 1989-1995 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Coordination and integration at all levels of government, 1989-1995 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Economic Development, General, 1989-1995 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Economic Development, Bond Issue, 1989-1995 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Economic Development, Comprehensive Economic Development Strategy Plan (H.D. No. 58), 1994 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Economic Development, Propose Recommendations to Improve and Enhance the Economic Development of the Southside Region of the Commonwealth, A Report to (H.D. No. 42), 1991 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Economic Development, Review of Economic Development in Virginia, Report of JLARC on (H.D. No. 39), 1991 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Economic Development, Virginia's Economic Development Policy, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Employment, 1989-1995 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Energy, Virginia Energy Patterns and Trends, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Environment, Alternative Wastewater, 1989-1995 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Environment, Bond Issue, Parks and Natural Areas, 1989-1995 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Environment, Critical Environmental Areas, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Environment, Environmental Impact Evaluation (Fairfax), 1991 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Environment, Environmental Quality, Dept. of, 1989-1995 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Environment, National Park Service REport on State Funding Programs Dedicated to Park, Recreation and Conservation Purposes, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Subject files, Environment, Piedmont Environmental Council, Workshop materials, 1992 (Box 5)